<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good mans refuge in affliction. Or A most profitable and comfortable sermon, preached by Iohn Barlovv. And now published especially for the good of them that bee, or haue been afflicted inwardly in minde, or outwardly in body</title>
            <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 695:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good mans refuge in affliction. Or A most profitable and comfortable sermon, preached by Iohn Barlovv. And now published especially for the good of them that bee, or haue been afflicted inwardly in minde, or outwardly in body</title>
                  <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop, vnder St. Peters Church in Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:1"/>
            <p>THE GOOD MANS REFVGE IN AF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FLICTION. <hi>OR</hi> A MOST PROFITABLE AND COMFORTABLE SERMON, preached by IOHN BARLOVV.</p>
            <p>AND NOW PVBLISHED ESPECI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the good of them that bee, or haue <hi>been afflicted inwardly in minde, or outwardly in body.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iudg. 6.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is with thee, thou valiant man.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Corn-hill. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR EDMVND TRYFOORD, OF TRY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FOORD, KNIGHT: <hi>I. B.</hi> WISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth truth of grace heere, glory <hi>eternall hereafter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N gratefulneſſe (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) hath been condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,<note place="margin">Plin. in prolog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſt.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Senec <hi>1</hi> de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficijs. ep <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> and reputed a vice to bee abandoned, and as a fruit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a wicked and an vnhappie minde.<note place="margin">Bernar ſup. Cant. Ch yſ ſuper Matth.</note> The Fathers too in former times haue auouched, that it is the enemie of the ſoule, the extenuation of deſert, the diſperſion of vertue, perdition of benefits; a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning winde, drying vp the fountaine of pietie, the ſpring of pittie, the influence of grace; and a ſinne that neuer goeth vnpuniſhed:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.17.</note> yea our Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes the nine Leapers, that they returned not to giue thankes for their cure;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 2.</note> and the Apoſtle makes it a damnable ſinne, that ſhall ſprout vp in the laſt dayes. Wherefore if I ſhould ſuffer the fauours to ſlip out of my minde, that I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:14514:3"/> from you, I could not cleere my ſelfe from the foule cenſure of an vngratefull perſon: But what haue I to render, except words, for all your kindneſſes? yet were they good, then might I bee glad, and you receiue ſome acceptable gratuitie; but howſoeuer they be, know, that had the Lord put better into my mouth, I had deliuered them willingly with my hand, and freely from my heart vnto you. I confeſſe that when I little expected any fauour from you, you furthered mee, not by word, but deed, in my ſtudies at the Vniuerſitie; and that not once, but often. And now I, (as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly, I iudge) haue ſent to your hands, one of the firſt fruits of my labours: in the manner there is ſome ſimilitude, but in the matter no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall proportion.</p>
            <p>Your Worſhip muſt not expect from mee curious diuiſion, rare inuention, Rhetoricall compoſition, or ambition of quotation: for I am one of the other day, a Babe pluckt from my mothers breaſt, by a kinde of force; and ſent to feed others, before I my ſelfe was well able to digeſt ſtronger meate, and bread of a harder concoction. But not to grow tedious, I preſume of your patronage, and willing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, though not for the dignitie of the worke, or deſert of the Authour (which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little); yet becauſe I know, you know, that Gifts are not to bee accepted or reiected, for their greatneſſe, and goodneſſe; but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in reſpect of the intention and affection of the giuer. And thus referring the worke to
<pb facs="tcp:14514:3"/> your Cenſure, and my ſelfe in all willingneſſe to doe you ſeruice, I commend you to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, who ſtabliſh you in euery good word, and worke, to doe his will. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all Seruices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he can ſtead you, <hi>IOHN BARLOVV.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14514:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN AND WELL AFFECTED READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, I freely confeſſe, that mans heart naturally is like to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; a little one will ſwell, grow big, and in a ſhort time puffe vp the whole lumpe of a mans perſon: and rare it is, not to be well conceited of our ſelues; not to iudge aboue the worth of our owne workes; and with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> not to thinke, that wee bee not ſome great bodies: But euery man knoweth beſt the beginning, and ſcope of all his proceedings. Wherefore though the ſetting out of Bookes may ſmell of vaine-glory, if not of folly, in theſe learned times; yet I am beſt acquainted with my owne heart, and full well vnderſtand mine owne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours: and were not I perſwaded, that (through the bleſſing of God) it would returne to thy further edification, theſe lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had neuer com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to light.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, I muſt giue thee to vnderſtand, that when I firſt treated of this ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct, it was (though a fault peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) within the City of London, and before one of the moſt indicious auditori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s there. But ſince that time, I haue had occaſion elſe where to proſecvte the text more at large; and diuers haue been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſir us to haue what I then deliuered, to be publiſhed iudging it to be not vnworthy the Preſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Now if I haue don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> amiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not mine owne, but many other mens errours are with me; the which If I bee blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-worthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as it is like
<pb facs="tcp:14514:5"/> enough) may ſerue in part, though not altogether, to excuſe me in this action. But and if I haue done well, Id ſire not, neither deſerue any praiſe, becauſe it was as much of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as willingly. I will not altog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe, or accuſe my ſelfe vnto thee: onely this (without preiudice to any) may bee ſpoken, that euery man hath his proper gift of God; whence it followeth, that the meaneſt ſcholer, ſometimes, in ſome thing, from this ground, may excell him, that in many things excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth others: the which either being not vnderſtood, or (as it ought) practiſed; makes men of good deſert contemned, and the graces of Gods ſpirit, reiected deſpiſed. Were he not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the title of a foole, that would neuer walke out of doores, becauſe all the Planets are not equall to the Sunne in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, brightneſſe? or deſerues not he to die for want of food, that will not eate, neither drinke, vntill he finde all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be like in kind, colour, and taſte? Who would not deeme him an vnskilfull Muſition, that will not ſtrike a ſtroke, except all the ſtrings be one and the ſame in quantitie and ſound? And he is no wiſer, that will reade no Authours, heare no Preachers, approue no mans labours, vntill there bee an equality in words, method and phraſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in reading, and hearing, try the ſpirit, ſee wherein the Gift of the perſon moſt conſiſteth, and then draw the water of life from that Pipe and Conduit: ſo ſhalt thou neither abuse thy owne wit, nor another mans worthineſſe. The which that thou maiſt doe, the Lord rectifie thy iudgement, and then encline the wheele of thy will (which is froward) to runne according to its direction. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus, IOHN BARLOVV.</signed> 
               <dateline>From my ſtudy at Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.
<date>Iune <hi>26. 1618.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14514:5"/>
            <head>THE GOOD MANS REFVGE IN AFFLICTION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 40.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I poore and needie, the Lord thinketh on me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been my priuate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that he who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a long Logicall Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis to a ſhort Sermon, may not vnfitly bee reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to an vndiſcreet Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueler, that deſcendeth from his horſe, entreth into the houſe, ſpendeth a couple of pence; yet when hee is to pay, draweth forth his purſe, and declareth thereby all the coyne in his pocket: for will not that be a griefe to the Hoſte, ſeeing ſo much, and receiuing no more? and a note of folly in the Gueſt, he ſpending ſo little, notwithſtanding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth all his treaſure? The application here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I leaue to your ſelues; reſoluing to imitate the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14514:6"/> skilfull husband, or well-experienced and expert Taylor: breaking vp no more ground, then I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſcatter with good graine; neither ſhaping that piece of cloth, I purpoſe not at this preſent to make vp into a garment.</p>
            <p>In theſe words therefore, of many, two things of me ſhall but be obſerued; the one is, the perſon; the other, his condition. For the perſon, it may be either meant of <hi>Dauid</hi> literally, or of <hi>Christ</hi> his Sonne (according to the fleſh) typically,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 30 9.</note> for <hi>Christ</hi> is often called <hi>Dauid</hi> by the <hi>Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5.</note> and of him this Pſalme alſo entreateth, as the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> teſtifieth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 105.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning his condition, it is twofold: firſt, he layeth downe his miſery, and in griefe of heart confeſſeth, that hee is <hi>poore and needy:</hi> the ſecond (which is the ground of raiſing vp his fainting ſpirit) hee annexeth, that <hi>yet,</hi> notwithſtanding, all the euill that hath befallen him, <hi>the Lord thinketh on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might ſpend much time, to ſhew you the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall readings of theſe words, and diuers expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by ſundry interpreters: but I haue reſpect to my promiſe; breuitie is my purpoſe, and my bounds I will not paſſe.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Perſon:</hi> eſpecially I vnderſtand <hi>Dauid;</hi> neither doe I exclude <hi>Christ,</hi> or any of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: for the ſeruant is not (in this reſpect) better then his Maſter; and betwixt the <hi>Head</hi> and all the other parts of the whole body, there is a ſympathy and fellow-feeling; let the condition be good, or bad; in earth or <hi>Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14514:6"/>
            <p>By <hi>poore and needy:</hi> I hold to be meant the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, and fierie trialls that come from <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> the tentations, and bitter aſſaults of that foule and fell fiend, <hi>Satan;</hi> the perſecutions and vexations inflicted by the hands of vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and wicked men; and (but in this following <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt bee exempted) the inward corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſordered motions, vnſetled affections, and the originall pollutions brought from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe; with the ſoule and bodies vnapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vnableneſſe with chearefulnes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, to runne the direct and iuſt paths of <hi>Gods</hi> commands. Many of theſe made the Head, all of theſe (and more too) the members, <hi>poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>the Lord:</hi> we may (I take it) without danger vnderſtand <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by <hi>Thinking on me;</hi> how that hee would free his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and all that he had giuen him, from all trouble, bondage and afflictions that euer ſhould befall them: for the father thought on his <hi>Sonne</hi> in the Garden, and vpon the <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe,</hi> when all had forſaken him: ſo hee did thinke on <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> when no man aſſiſted them: and, as wee ſhall heare more at large anone; ſo hath he, doth he, and will hee thinke vpon all his choſen, <hi>head</hi> and members.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all in one word is this, as if <hi>Christ, Dauid,</hi> or any true beleeuer had thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What if I be poore, afflicted, deſpiſed and perſecuted? What if the Lord ſeeme to leaue mee for a time, as one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14514:7"/> forſaken? and fallen into the hands of his cruel enemies? hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he therefore forgotten me? forſaken me? No, no: he know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th me by name, his eye of pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uidence is ſtill ouer me; and I am con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nt in this ſame thing, that he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ree me from all euil, and preſerue me to his heauen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, according to my purpoſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, I come to handle the ſeuerall doctrines, that hence, without wrong to my Text, or offence to any iudicious Auditor, may be deduced: where firſt let it be obſerued, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Af i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ions befall Gods dearest children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnderſtand this Text to bee prophecied of <hi>Christ:</hi> canſt thou denie the truth of the doctrine? was it no ſorrow to his humane Nature,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, whipped and crucified? what a burden bare he? what a wounded ſpirit had he? and what woe endured he? when he ſweat great drops of bloud; called to his Diſciples to <hi>watch with him;</hi> and cried out,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.</note> 
               <hi>My ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule is heauy to death; My God, my God, why hast thou forſaken me?</hi> Were not theſe piercing ſorrowes? But we leaue the Head, and come to touch ſome of his members; and but touch, leſt wee grow tedious. Shall I relate <hi>Abel</hi> ſuddenly ſlaine by cruell <hi>Caine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 48. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10.</note> his bloudy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall brother? <hi>Abrahams</hi> flight, he knew not thither? or <hi>Iaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> heauy iourney to <hi>Padan Aram?</hi> Were it to the purpoſe, to tell you of <hi>Moſes, Ioſeph, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b,</hi> or any of the <hi>Prophets?</hi> Is it a ſorrow to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 2.</note> to haue al ones children ſlaine in a moment? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to be perſecuted for well-doing? May it bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled, a pricke, or wound, to faſt often? to bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14514:7"/> whipt often? to be impriſoned wrongfully often?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 11.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to die often in appearance once in truth, and that vniuſtly? Why then the point is confirmed, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke</hi> 235.</note> that a ſword <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth pierce through the hearts of Gods deareſt children. And though this at the firſt ſeeme ſtrange; yet you ſhall ſee (at the laſt) it will ſtand with right reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For <hi>Chriſt,</hi> had not he ſuffred, who had been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? and if he had not been pierced through with many ſorrowes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3.5. <hi>&amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> not one of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> had poſſeſſed any true comfort, or ſound ſolace. And for this end, it was needfull to conſecrate the Prince of their ſaluation through afflictions.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.11.</note> He was that brazen Altar, which muſt vndergoe the great heate of the day,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 8 30.</note> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which fier was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually burning: <hi>Chriſt</hi> was typified or figured hereby, to ſuffer the infinite iuſtice of his father.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> And his members muſt be like the buſh in the fier, for ſeuerall reaſons. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Are they not the Lords (as I may ſay) garden-plots?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 32.</note> will he not plant and ſowe them with the ſweeteſt ſeedes, and moſt fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant flowers? ſhall he not then digge them vp,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 4 4.</note> picke out the leaſt graſſe, and breake euery little clod to pieces? Euery skilfull Gardener doth this to that plot of ground, where he intendeth to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grapes, and not thornes; figs, and not thiſtles. And ſo it is with the Lord; where he will ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the good graine of his grace, that perſon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſhall haue piercing ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, the faithfull are likened to trees, and muſt not they be pruned and lopped?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.3.</note> If they that were planted in <hi>Eden,</hi> muſt be kept,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and dreſſed by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14514:8"/> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> our father? ſhall wee thinke to eſcape the knife to cut vs and prune vs? for trees, if the roots runne to deepe into the earth, they muſt bee cut ſhorter; if the branches ſpread too farre, they muſt be lopped; and if the Canker or Caterpiller once infect, and cleaue to them, then they muſt be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſmoaked: ſo (aſſuredly) if wee bee too much rooted, by our affections, in the things of the world; and with the great and large boughes of our abilitie, wrong and impoueriſh our poore neighbour; or let our coyne, like the canker, eate into our ſoules; God will giue vs many a cutting, lopping and ſmoaking: and as wee cannot natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally but doe the one; ſo, when God will heale vs ſpiritually, he will doe the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Moreouer, Gods children are compared to good corne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13.24.</note> not cockle; wee muſt expect then to be ſhaken with the windie and bluſtring ſtormes of the wicked.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.25.</note> The Rookes of our times will bee pecking out the ripeſt graine; and euerie raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fowle flie ouer vs, and defile vs; goe thorow vs, and bruiſe vs; or fall vpon vs, and rob vs: yea, our God himſelfe will cut vs downe, threſh vs, and grind vs; for its corne that muſt bee put on the mill, not chaffe: wheate that muſt be winnowed, when cockle is to be abandoned, burned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Beſides this, how often are the godly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Temple?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.</note> and may not euery particular perſon reſemble a ſtone in diuers things? Wee muſt be cut out of the rocke of our naturall eſtate;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.</note> and it's no eaſie matter to be endured, afterwards ſquared and hewen, that we may be fitted to lie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14514:8"/> cloſe and comely in the building: and this will be felt a paineful poliſhing; yet this muſt be done, or we are vndone. Rough ſtones are caſt into the foundation, but they that be appointed for the <hi>Pinnacles,</hi> and principall places, muſt haue the more pickes, the greater poliſhing: elſe they ſhould not bee of (or at the beſt but deface) this holy Temple, this ſtately building. And becauſe that this is not the chief point in my text, though the words (in part) will beare it; wee will make briefe application, and ſo proceede to another.</p>
            <p>And doe piercing ſorrowes befal Gods deareſt children? what vſe then is to be made of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Why, the wicked may here learne a leſſon; its a true one (for <hi>Peter</hi> drawes it from this ground) but a terrible one to all ſuch perſons. If iudgment begin at the houſe of God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall the end bee of thoſe that obey not the Goſpell of Chriſt?</hi> and, <hi>If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinner appeare?</hi> Another Apoſtle tells you,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8.</note> and giues you a full reſolution: <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall come in flaming fier, to render vengeance vpon them that know him not, and obey not the Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi> This is not all, for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall be puniſhed with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting perdition</hi> (that's their end) <hi>from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glorie of his power</hi> (that is the place of their appearance).</p>
            <p>But wicked men imagine, that God is like them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</note> becauſe for a time he holds his peace; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard iudgement, a little ſeaſon is deferred, the hearts of the ſonnes of earthly men are ſet vpon<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 8.11.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14514:9"/> miſchief.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 1.12.</note> Tuſh (ſay ſuch) God wil neither do good or euill: But, O thou vaine man, when wilt thou learne wiſdome! ſhall he ſcourge his firſt borne, his onely ſonne, and but by imputation a ſinner? and doeſt thou thinke that he wil ſpare thee? Shal the naturall O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue bee thus lopped, and pruned? and ſhal the wild One eſcape the hand of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man? Will the Creditor cauſe the ſurety to pay all to the vttermoſt farthing? and doeſt thou, that art ſo deep in debt, expecta diſcharge without full paiment? Is the path to <hi>Canaan</hi> thus ſtrawed? what then will the way be that leadeth to Egypt?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 10 33.</note> if he that trembleth at Gods word, ſhall thus bee corrected; how ſhall they, that make a mocke of the bloud of the new Couenant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.29.</note> eſcape damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Tell, if thou canſt, but its a thing impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Hee that goeth towards the Sunne, ſhall haue his ſhadow follow him; but he that runneth from it, to flee before him: So he that marcheth with his face towards the <hi>Sonne</hi> of righteouſneſſe, ſhall haue afflictions ſtill to purſue him; as for him that hath his backe towards Chriſt; his ſorrowes, like the ſhadow, are before him; but hee ſhall meete with them in another world. Wherefore be thou not deceiued; for if God afflict his deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he will one day take vengeance of all diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient baſtards.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And to what vſe ſhall the godly put this <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine?</hi> Why, they muſt not thinke it ſtrange, that they are in the fierie triall;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 12.</note> neither faint becauſe they are chaſtened: for its for thy good, and the Lords glorie, that theſe things befall thee. <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14514:9"/> is a ſhepheard, and they that ſerue him are ſheepe, by the rule of relation: ſhall he not then ſend this Dogge of affliction, to fetch vs in, when we breake our bounds, and are ſtragling? hee is our Maſter, and wee his ſcholers; muſt wee not then haue a laſh, when our eye is off our booke; and wee haue no mind, either to ſay, or learne our leſſon? we bee his patients, he our Phiſition; then if wee feed too full, grow too ranke, ſhall he not ſtrike a vaine, and let vs blood, in due ſeaſon?</p>
            <p>I haue often in my meditations, compared a <hi>Christian</hi> in proſperity, to a people at peace in a kingdome: doe we not ſee, that ſince warres haue ceaſed in our land, and neighbour Countries, that many a valiant ſouldier is growne fat, purfie, and not able to weild his weapons? And all (or the moſt) of our Armour to, ruſtie, cankred? The Spiders haue wouen webs in our Helmets, and head-pieces: the wormes eate into the very heart and pith of our ſhafts and ſpeares; and ſcarce is to bee found any Bandileeres, that will hold to hang about a ſouldiers ſholders. Are not our ſhips vnrigged? our Cannons at the Forts, vnskoured? houſes, townes, and Cities, but too weakely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided? And hath not peace (by accident) had a finger in this buſineſſe? And euen ſo is it with a Chriſtian ſouldier; let him haue health of body, quiet of mind, and his cups to flow ouer; all his ſpirituall armour will either ruſt, or bee vnexerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. For what vſe ſhall we haue of prayer, in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; faith, in beleeuing; hope, in expecting; or patience, in ſuffering? truly little, if any at all:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14514:10"/> therefore God will ſend warres, and rumours of warres, that wee may not abuſe thoſe excellent graces, and hee want his glory, wee our gaine by them.</p>
            <p>Our God is wiſe, yea <hi>Wiſdome</hi> it ſelfe, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our eſtates, and can phyſicke vs for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and there is nothing ſo bad, but hee can vſe for the recouery of our former condition, and cauſe it to worke for good. I remember, that when <hi>Ioab</hi> would not come to <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.30.31.</note> he ſet his corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field on fier, and thereby fetcht him: ſo when the iuſt Ones will not ſee their fathers face,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>and</hi> 5.15.</note> the fier of affliction will make them ſeeke him early, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently. It is the cuſtome of our Gallants, when their horſes bee ſlow and dull, to ſpurre them; if iron grow ruſty, caſt it into the fier to purifie it: and ſo doth our good God, in our backwardneſſe to good duties, pricke vs; or being in our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, purifie vs, by caſting vs into the hot coales of tribulation.</p>
            <p>Wherefore doe not ſo much mourne, that thou art afflicted; but be carefull and fearfull, leſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou ſhould not be reformed; for this is a true ſigne that we are Gods ſonnes, and not baſtards, when wee are more doubtfull that wee ſhall not make the right vſe of them, then fearfull that the Lord will not remoue them. He that findeth this in himſelfe, findeth a good thing, and but that which alwaies attendeth and accompanieth a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified heart in its greateſt troubles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> But ſome man may ſay; Sir, it is a hard thing to ſuffer afflictions patiently; therefore what ſhall I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14514:10"/> doe to attaine to this?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſol. </seg>1</label> Why, thou muſt conſider, that it is the direct path to heauen;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.13.</note> and is it not better to bee in our right way, though ſtonie, crooked; then in the pleaſant Medowes going aſtray, wandring? The ſpeedieſt way to compaſſe the world, is to goe by water; and the ſureſt path to heauen, is to ſaile through a ſea of affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſol. </seg>2</label> Againe, call to mind that <hi>Christ</hi> thy Captaine hath trod the ſame ſteps before thee; and ſhall not the Head be followed by the members? It is ſaid,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30.</note> that <hi>Dauid the King went vp to the Mount of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues, and the people with him, and as they went, they wept:</hi> ſo our <hi>Dauid</hi> is aſcended into heauen, but he went weeping, and ſo muſt we follow him wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; for theſe two are inſeparable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſol. </seg>3</label> Moreouer, ponder with thy owne ſoule, how many, how great troubles, thou by thy ſinnes haſt innumerable times deſerued? Alas!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.39.</note> long agoe mighteſt thou haue been cut off by death, and condemned: if this were thought on, it would ſtoppe this vaine of diſcontent and impatience. Thou maiſt admire thou waſt not long agoe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, rather then pine, in that thou art corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, afflicted.</p>
            <p>Finally, immoderate mourning, is a meanes to draw downe a heauier iudgement. When boyes will pule, and cry out for a little laſh, the Maſter many times ſets it on with a tang: And hee that will ſtruggle vnder the Lords hand, peraduenture ſhall vndergoe a double ierking. Say therefore with <hi>Dauid, I held my peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39 9.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou Lord diddeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14514:11"/> it.</hi> Thus much for this point; the ſecond ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, which is, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>The Lord doth not ſeparate his affection from his children in affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.1.</note>Howeuer it be, <hi>yet God is good to Iſrael; and the pure in heart ſhall neuer be forgotten.</hi> Did not hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 8 1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.</note> in his Arke? <hi>Abraham,</hi> in all his troubles? <hi>Iacob,</hi> in his heauie iourney? <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> in the pit and priſon?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 16. <hi>Gen</hi> 39.21. <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.16.</note> and iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> in the middeſt of <hi>Sodome?</hi> The Lord thought on <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee kept his fathers ſheepe: <hi>Saul</hi> would haue ſlaine him;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ziklag</hi> was burnt, in his flight to <hi>Gath;</hi> and when he had forgotten his God, committed adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and murther, and was in his greateſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how often doth this man confeſſe, that in the middeſt of all his ſorrowes <hi>the Lord comforted his ſoule?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 94.19.</note> and, <hi>Though his father and his mother ſhould forſake him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.10.</note> 
               <hi>yet Iehouah would gather him?</hi> I might here make mention of <hi>Moſes, Daniel, the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and <hi>our fore-runner, Christ;</hi> and tell me, which of the faithfull was euer forgotten by the Lord? He hath ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5.</note> that <hi>He will not leaue vs, or forſake vs;</hi> but at all times, and in all places, he will bee with vs. <hi>Paul,</hi> without doubting, caſteth downe the gantlet, and biddeth a defiance againſt all things, (which notably doth proue the point in hand). <hi>Who,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or what ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of God? ſhall tribulation, or anguiſh, or famine, or perſecution, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or the ſword? No: for hee is perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come; nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14514:11"/> ſhall bee able to ſeparate the faithfull from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Shall I now ſhew it you in the Reaſon?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, the Lord is not ſubiect to forgetfulneſſe, he <hi>knoweth who are his;</hi> and <hi>his eye is alwaies ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 19.</note> Could the Lord forget them, were hee ſubiect to ignorance? then his affections might be ſeparate from them; but he is not, he cannot. <hi>Tamar</hi> may diſguiſe her ſelfe, walke in an vnaccuſtomed path; ſo <hi>Iudah</hi> may not know her. <hi>Iſaac,</hi> through the dimneſſe of his ſight, may bleſſe <hi>Iacob,</hi> and paſſe <hi>Eſau.</hi> Tract of time may make <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to forget, or be forgotten of his brethren. <hi>Salomon</hi> may doubt to whom the child (of certaine) belongeth; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> come to his owne, and not bee receiued. But the Lord ſeeth all his; time, place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13.</note> ſpeech or apparell cannot obſcure or darken his eye or eare. He can diſcerne <hi>Daniel</hi> in the denne; <hi>Iob,</hi> though neuer ſo changed, on the dunghill: Let <hi>Ionah</hi> haue his lodging in the whales belly; <hi>Peter</hi> be put into cloſe priſon; or <hi>Lazarus</hi> bee wrapped in rags; or <hi>Abel</hi> tumbling in blood; yet can hee call them by name, and ſend his Angels to comfort them. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, or forgetfulneſſe may cauſe loue to bee eſtranged in the creature; but the Lord is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to either: for his eye, as his eſſence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139 1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where. In this reſpect therefore he needeth not to ſeparate his affection from his children in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> And as the Lord is not ſubiect to forget, ſo is he not incident to change; for <hi>whom he loueth once,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal</hi> 3 6. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.3.</note> 
               <hi>he loueth euer.</hi> Man is ſubiect to mutation of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14514:12"/> but ſo is not the Lord: for he is one moſt pure act, his loue makes vs good; ſo that his affection is perpetuall. Mans iudgement may deceiue him, and his loue cannot make the obiect beloued bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; therefore hee is ſubiect to alteration; God not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But we reade that God hath repented, and ſo changed his affection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>1</label> I anſwere, firſt, that it is ſpoken for our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, after the manner of man, and not to bee vnderſtood otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>2</label> Againe, the change is not in God, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the obiect about which hee is exerciſed; for one cauſe without alteration in it ſelfe may produce diuers effects in that regard. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: The <hi>Sunne</hi> hath but one ſimple act of ſhining; yet, doe wee not ſee that it doth vnite clay and ſtraw, diſſolue ice into water? makes the flowers ſmell ſweetly, and a dead corpſe to ſtinke loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly? the hot fier to be colder, and the cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hotter? and will it not helpe to cure one man by his heate, yet therewith kill another? Where is the cauſe? in the ſeuerall obiects, and their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers diſpoſitions, and conſtitutions; and not in the Sunnes act of ſhining, which is but one and the ſame.</p>
            <p>Take a more familiar ſimilitude. Let a look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſe be ſet in the window, will it not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to thy eye diuers obiects? If thou goe to it in decent and comely apparell, ſhalt not thou ſee the like figure? if deiected, and in courſe rayment, will it not offer to thy view the ſame equall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14514:12"/> doe but thou ſtretch thy ſelfe, bend thy brow, and runne againſt it, and will it not reſemble the like perſon, and action? where is the change? ſhall we conclude in the glaſſe? No: for it is neither altered from the place, nor in nature.</p>
            <p>Wherefore if God one day ſeeme to loue vs, another day to hate vs; there is an alteration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs firſt, not any in the Lord. Bee thou then ſuch in thy ſelfe, as thou wouldeſt haue the Lord bee vnto thee; but if thou change, thou ſhalt finde a change, though God neuer change; and if thou runne ſtubburnly againſt him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.24.25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> he will <hi>walke ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnly</hi> againſt thee. For <hi>with the froward, hee will ſhew himſelfe froward; but with the meeke, hee will ſhew himſelfe meeke.</hi> Yea, ſuch as thou art to him, he will be to thee, and no other. O that we could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and ſo practice this leſſon!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> To proceed; let vs examine and ſee, what is the cauſe of ſeparating affection; and ſhall wee not finde it either in the Agent or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect? In the louer, <hi>God,</hi> we ſee no cauſe can bee found: ſurely, nor in the thing beloued. For what is affliction to Gods children? doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the eſſence of the ſoule, or deface the image of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe in them?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 22.44. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71.</note> Doth it (in a word) make them worſe, or better? It is plaine, that no trouble deſtroyeth the image of God; or maketh his the more prone to ſinne; but rather it hath been a meanes to moue them to leaue it and amend. For in trouble they will pray more feruently;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note> pity others more compaſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; make vowes, and reſolue to ſerue God the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14514:13"/> more ſtrictly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.13.14.</note> then euer in the dayes of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Why then ſhould the Lord withdraw his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from them? for loue leaues hold, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the obiect growes worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> And in the laſt place, this Reaſon may alſo confirme the doctrine. Hee ſhould bee more vnnaturall then meere naturall men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.9.10 11.</note> (who take the moſt pitie of their owne being in the greateſt diſtreſſe) if he ſhould forſake his children in their affliction.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</note> Nature it ſelfe, in theſe ſtraits, will not be wanting; and ſhall the Author of all graces be found failing?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note> Shall <hi>Dauid</hi> keepe ſuch a houling for a rebellious ſonne? and will the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy</hi> not reſpect his obedient children? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with it: for it is a kind of blaſphemy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. For betwixt the loue of the Creator, and the creature, there is neither in reſpect of heighth, depth, breadth, or length, any equall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> And is this ſo? how then ſhould we loue ſuch a God, of whom wee are ſo beloued? what praiſe ſhould we thinke too much for ſo waighty a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? why doe we not ſtudie to ſet forth his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and wonderfull workes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> would make a ſong, <hi>Dauid</hi> and others in way of thankfulneſſe, becauſe in their greateſt affliction, they felt the Lord to be preſent in affection. Did not <hi>Mary</hi> breake out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.46.47.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule ſhall magnifie the name of the Lord, and my ſpirit ſhall reioyce in God my Sauiour?</hi> Why did ſhe this? <hi>for hee hath looked on the poore eſtate of his handmaid.</hi> How did <hi>Paul,</hi> from the like ground double his petition; <hi>The Lord ſhew mercy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14514:13"/> to the houſe of Oneſiphorus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16.18.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord grant that he may find mercy with the Lord in that day:</hi> VVhere was the reaſon of this? <hi>for he found me out at Rome, viſited me often at Epheſus, and was not aſhamed of my chaine.</hi> Shall the Apoſtle thus bleſſe his friend, for being refreſhed in his bands? and ſhall not we, from the heart rootes, break forth into thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe? For God, not once, but often hath viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs, and hath not been aſhamed of our chaines of ſinne and corruption: nay, he hath broke our bands, and ſet vs, that were Satans ſlaues, at free liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But ſome may ſay to me, as many ſhall to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the laſt day; <hi>When ſaw we thee in nakedneſſe, &amp;c?</hi> ſo, VVhen were wee poore and needy, and <hi>God</hi> thought on vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Giue me leaue a little, and I will tell you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of all, doe but caſt the eye of your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance backe, and runne with the feete of your faith ſo farre, as the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> our father;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> did not we eate with him, ſinne with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14.17.</note> and lay in the buſh with him? was not he, and all we at that time poore and needie? who was euer in ſo great a ſtreight? in ſo miſerable a condition? conceiue, if thou canſt, of a portion of matter without a forme; and ſuch was thy tickle condition, almoſt turn'd to nothing: were we not all dead men, and depriued of our greateſt glorie?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.</note> what mans caſe was euer more miſerable then all ours, before the Lord called, <hi>Adam, Where art thou?</hi> Conceiue of it a little, lay it to heart, ponder it deepely in thy mind, and ſuffer it to take ſome ſetled impreſſion.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14514:14"/> What miſerie was that? What a word of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort was this, <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhall ſhuffle or breake the Serpents head?</hi> I ſpeake to you that haue vnderſtanding, and conſider what I ſay; for the more thou doeſt meditate on this thing, it will ſeeme to thee the more wonderfull.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But let vs come neerer home, and then will it not appeare, that we in this our Kingdome, were ſometimes poore and needie? And becauſe too many crie out, and (as the ſpies did vpon <hi>Canaan</hi>) haue brought a bad report vpon our countrie; let vs ſearch into, and examine the matter. And that we may ſpeak as the thing is, let vs firſt of al com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the land with it ſelf, and next with her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring ſiſters.</p>
            <p>Was it not in times paſt, as at the beginning, a <hi>Chaos, without forme and voide?</hi> Did not <hi>darkeneſſe couer</hi> all our <hi>deepe?</hi> and <hi>the people periſh for want of knowledge?</hi> Ignorance was our wedding garment, and <hi>Implicite faith,</hi> a <hi>ſword</hi> faſt in the ſheath to <hi>quench all the fierie darts of Satan:</hi> our Bible was as a <hi>ſealed booke;</hi> the teachers of it <hi>blind guides,</hi> and <hi>Gods houſe nothing</hi> elſe but a <hi>Denne</hi> of <hi>Theeues.</hi> Were not all our Progenitors vnder this cloud? Did not ſinne enlarge it ſelfe, as <hi>Hell?</hi> and like the Leproſie in the time of the Law, ſpread farre, and infect the whole body? What were all the moſt eminent and pleaſant ſeates in our Kingdom, but hiues full of droanes; Temples, ſwarming with Caterpillers, who nipt euery greene thing in the bud, as in the land of <hi>Egypt?</hi> VVhat ſhall I more ſay? VVere not all our Prieſts Papiſts, or Atheiſts?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14514:14"/> Theſe places, wherein now in <hi>Spirit and truth</hi> the Lord is ſerued, a very ſinke of all ſinne, and <hi>Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of all vncleanneſſe? Is not this truth? And hath not the Lord in theſe latter daies brought light out of darkeneſſe? made the Engliſh man in <hi>his owne image?</hi> blowne part of this viperous brood into the red ſea of deſtruction? and giuen him his elder brothers bleſſing? I lye not: there is not one thing, at the which I haue more wondred, then to ſee how the Lord hath rooted out the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanite,</hi> who was ſo mighty, in number many, and equall in pride and malice; I doe not doubt to ſpeake, but if ſome of vs had ſeene the daies of old, and compared them to theſe, they would be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied at Gods goodneſſe, and the times reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For did not our Aunceſtors want the bread of the ſoule, the eye of the mind, and the pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life and ſaluation? Is it not to bee feared, that millions of ſoules were poiſoned, that I ſay not eternally damned? Look back the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take a ſtrict view what ſhe was, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what ſhe is; we account compariſons odious; but I am ſure, ſuch as theſe, be commodious: and he that doth not compare time with time, ſhall neuer ſee the depth of mans miſerie, or the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lords mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But me thinkes I heare ſome in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſay, I goe beyond my bounds, and giue my Countrie too good a commendation. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> I do not, nor cannot, ſo the rule bee obſerued: ſhee is farre better then ſhe hath been, yet in many things ſhe might be mended. God called not all his works
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14514:15"/> 
               <hi>very good,</hi> before the laſt daies Creation; no more will I my Mother, vntill the laſt day of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and recreation: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> But yet I may ſay, and muſt ſay, ſhe is well amended. And in the ſecond place, doe but compare our Iland with others neare ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning; are not they more <hi>poore and needy</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things then we be? and did not the <hi>Lord</hi> then herein <hi>thinke vpon vs?</hi> Haue not we a great Light to rule the day, and many leſſe for the night-ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? What if ſome wandring Planets bee in the firmament? why, is not their irregular courſe and motion euident to all men?</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Canaauites</hi> had been deſtroyed at once, the beaſts of the field had deuoured the Iſraelites: and what knoweſt thou, but the ſame reaſon may be of force in theſe daies? Let vs not murmure, ſeeing we haue tooke poſſeſſion of their land, and haue dominion ouer the Canaanite: Wee haue the prize, and the remnant one day ſhall be ours, if our ſinnes and ingratefulneſſe doe not preuent it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>3</label> I could tel you of particulars, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were <hi>poore and needy, and the Lord thought on vs,</hi> at the change of the two Princes: Did not the Edomites con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that then was the day of mourning, when they intended to be reuenged of Iſrael? But God preuented them. And in 88 was not lots caſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our land, and we eſteemed as dead men? And in (that neuer to be forgotten deliuery) the Gun-powder-plot, were not all our heads neare the blocke? who was euer needy, if then we were not in need? VVhen I haue thought of that cruell
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14514:15"/> plot &amp; inuention, me ſeemes I could neuer match it, except that in the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and betwixt them there is ſome equall parallell.</p>
            <p>In that, there was the <hi>Diuell</hi> and the <hi>Serpent;</hi> the Garden and the perſons againſt whom the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was intended: and in this the Pope, <hi>Faux</hi> his inſtrument, the place, and the people they aimed at. And in this compariſon or allegorie, we liken the Pope to the Diuell; <hi>Faux</hi> to the Serpent; the Parliament-houſe to the Garden; and the King to <hi>Adam.</hi> The Diuell was in the Serpent, but would not bee ſeene; the Pope in <hi>Faux,</hi> yet loath to be diſcouered: the Serpent muſt ſwimme (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) in the water, and creepe cloſe into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; <hi>Faux</hi> muſt croſſe the ſeas, and crawle vnder the Parliament-houſe: the Serpent muſt ſpeake nothing, but as the Diuell would; nor <hi>Faux</hi> doe any thing, but by the Popes direction: the Diuell pretends kindneſſe to <hi>Adam, Yee ſhall be as Gods;</hi> the Pope vnder the cloake of holineſſe aimes at deſtruction: the Serpent reſpected not the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the place, to effect his purpoſe; nor <hi>Faux,</hi> if he might accompliſh his reſolued treaſon: the Serpent ſaid, <hi>Yee ſhall not die at all; Faux,</hi> if he had been poſed, would haue rendred the ſame leſſon: the Diuell in tempting <hi>Adam,</hi> aimed at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all his poſteritie; ſo did the Pope, in our dread Soueraigne, at all his royall iſſue, and loyall ſubiects: and in many more particulars they might be paralleld. And vndoubtedly theſe two plots (not to be equald by any) had one firſt efficient, Satan; twinnes they be, conceiued in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14514:16"/> ſame wombe; whether in Hell, or ſome Friers Cloyſter, there's the Queſtion. But how good was <hi>God</hi> to vs, that though they traueld of iniquitie, <hi>and conceiued miſchiefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.</note> 
               <hi>yet they haue brought forth a lie; their heads haue been bruiſed, and their counſell confounded?</hi> Suppoſe that it had tooke effect, what fact (except that in the Garden) to this had been comparable! For the walles of our <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had been ruinated, and the Sepulchers of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burnt with fier: our Annointed had died the death, and <hi>Bethel</hi> his houſe become a <hi>Babylon:</hi> our Harpes had been <hi>hanged on the willowes,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> (at the beſt) but <hi>ſung our Hebrew ſongs in a ſtrange</hi> tune, voyce and <hi>land: This was the worke of God, and ought to be marueilous in our eyes.</hi> For had not the Lord thought on vs, <hi>we had been ſwallowed vp quick, and laid as low as the nethermost hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>4</label> I omit many other miſeries, which made vs <hi>poore and needy;</hi> as pinching Froſts, ſcorching heate, inundations of waters, droughts, famine, and the deuouring plague in this City, and other places of our kingdome? VVas it not to bee <hi>poore and needie,</hi> when thouſands in a weeke depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? men, women and children drawn with hooks by heapes into holes? they that were liuing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther running away with great feare, or ſtaying ſtill at home, with greater? And who hath remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe euils, and ſent downe the contrary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings? Is it not the Lord? VVe haue but yet ſpoke of generals; but let vs deſcend to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and there's not one can deny, but in theſe two reſpects he hath been poore and needy; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14514:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lord thought on him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, for his corporall condition. VVho pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued thee in thy Mothers wombe? fed thee with Manna in this wilderneſſe? and freed thee from ſo many iudgements as haue been inflicted vpon others? Surely the hand of the Lord. VVho lead thee into greene paſtures, hath cauſed thy cup to <hi>flow ouer, and anoynted thee aboue thy fellowes,</hi> except <hi>Dauids Shepheard?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But to let theſe things paſſe: Art thou now the ſonne of God? waſt thou not the child of wrath by nature? who hath ſingled thee out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed multitude, enriched thee with the graces of ſaluation, and borne thee againe? whereas <hi>the whole world lyeth in wickedneſſe?</hi> VVill not theſe former fauours prouoke thee to gratefulneſſe? yet let the benefit by it for the preſent, and future time, bee forcible to vrge thee to the practice of this dutie: for others of Gods ſeruants haue done the ſame vpon no other ground. <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee conſidered, that <hi>The Lord had aſsiſted him, when all men for ſpoke him,</hi> and was perſwaded, that <hi>the Lord would deliuer him from euery euill worke, and preſerue him to his heauenly Kingdome;</hi> breakes forth into theſe words, <hi>To whom be praiſe for euer and euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And is not this paterne worthie of our beſt imitation? and this conſtant affection on the Lords part, a continuall gratuitie on ours? VVhy then let it be daily put in practiſe: for either this loue, or nothing deſerues it, and is thankſworthie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And as this point in the firſt place ſhould work in vs loue autogratefulneſſe to God: ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14514:17"/> it may comfort vs for the preſent and future troubles. Haſt thou vexations without, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors within? ſeemes it to thee, that the Lord hath forſaken thee? Why, it is not ſo: thou art decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Think on the dayes of old, and if euer thou canſt proue, that he did loue thee; this point will proue he doth ſo ſtill. What ſhould more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort a Chriſtians heart then this? and encourage him to go on through good report, and euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with reſolution?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.38.</note>VVhat made the people weepe ſo bitterly, and fall on <hi>Pauls</hi> necke? was it not, in that they muſt <hi>ſee his face no more?</hi> And what did <hi>Christ</hi> promiſe to his diſciples for their comfort and reſolution in their greateſt troubles and vexations? Any thing but this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> 
               <hi>I will bee with you to the end of the world:</hi> You then that haue choſen the better part, giuen vp your names to ſerue God, and bee in the vaſt wildernes of this world, be not faint, or weary in the way: for though hunger pinch you, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> purſue you, and the fierie Serpents ſting you, yet the <hi>Lord ſhall neuer leaue you, or forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> But ſome may obiect to me, as <hi>Gedeon</hi> did to the Angell;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>Ah my Lord, if the Lord loue vs, and be with vs; why then is all this euill come vpon vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>Art thou ſicke in body? the Lord doth it for to make it a fitter habitation for thy ſoule. VVhat if thou ſeeme to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in pieces? yet he can eaſily reſtore thee to thy former conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Shal you not ſee a Carpenter ſet vp a houſe in a comely order, yet anon he wil ſtrike one ioynt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, &amp; lay it flat on the ground? hath he a purpoſe to deſtroy it?</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14514:17"/>
            <p>No: rather to amend what he ſaw amiſſe in it: And ſo be we, in our owne iudgements, builded in a decent manner; but <hi>God is wiſe in heart,</hi> and ſeeth that our bodies are not fit Temples for his Spirit; therefore we muſt downe againe for a time (at the leaſt) in our owne feeling, &amp; preſent apprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But thou wilt ſay, The ſpirit is departed from thee, and not to be found within thee.</p>
            <p>Thou art to know this,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> that in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſoule there be many manſions; as of loue, ioy, faith, zeale, repentance, and humility: If therefore the ſpirit be not preſent in one place, ſeeke to finde him in another: for be thou aſſured hee is not (in truth) departed. Doeſt thou want ioy, or faith? canſt thou pray for either? why thou haſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Canſt thou not pray? (for ſometimes this is a good mans condition), yet canſt thou ſigh and grone? why, that commeth from the Spirit: Canſt thou not repent as in times paſt? art thou notwithſtanding ſenſible of this? and ſtrikeſt thy hand vpon thy breaſt? this is a motion of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And be thou of good comfort; for when thy caſe ſpirituall is moſt miſerable, yet thou maieſt diſcerne ſome pulſe (though weake) of the Spirit, beating. He that comes to ſee his friend, will bee glad to finde him in any roome of his houſe; and if he be not in the dining chamber, or parlour, hee (peraduenture) ſhall haue him in ſome other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate corner: ſo, if the Spirit be abſent from the manſions of faith, loue, and the like: then thou muſt finde him out in the cloſe and darke roome, called, The diſlike of thy preſent condition; or in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14514:18"/> the ſecret corner of <hi>Humiliation.</hi> Theſe two be the furtheſt places of his abſence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> But I was vſed to haue him preſent in all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solution.</note>To ſpeake with reuerence; Euery grace in our hearts may bee compared to ſo many candles in a houſe: Now the Maſter will not light aboue one or two at the moſt, except hee haue great vſe of them: ſo the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is the keeper of our ſoules; he worketh with theſe graces in vs; and hee will but employ them, as there is iuſt occaſion: If there bee need, all ſhall bee enlightened, made ſtrong. And what man being an old Diſciple, that hath not experience in theſe things?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>4</label> Why, how can the Lord be with vs? <hi>for they that worke wickedneſſe are ſet vp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ſuch as tempt God, they are deliuered:</hi> And are not all things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, and without vs, out of order?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solution.</note>We muſt not iudge things by the appearance or preſent condition; for then we may <hi>condemne the generation of the iuſt</hi> and the Lords owne buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: He that would haue comfort in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his houſe, muſt not conceiue of it in parts: as of the wood in the Forreſts, vnſquared; the ſtone in the rockes, vnpoliſhed; the brick in the clay, vnburned; and lime in the ſand, vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered; but in the patterne or frame, as it will bee when it is perfected: So wee are to looke at the end of the righteous, and the reſtauration of all things, not as they bee for the preſent; and then ſhall we ſee the full beauty of the Lords workes, and our owne bleſſedneſſe. <hi>He that doth theſe things ſhall neuer fall,</hi> finally, and for euer.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14514:18"/>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Watch ye, ſtand ye faſt, quit you like men, and be ſtrong:</hi> for the Lords affection to all the faithfull, neuer faileth in affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> And doth not the Lord ſeparate his affection from his children in affliction? Let vs then tread in the ſame ſteps, and imitate our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Oh that this were the cuſtome of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey! but it is not; we rather practice the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, adding affliction to <hi>Pauls</hi> bands. For <hi>to him that hath not</hi> (need of comfort) <hi>ſhall bee giuen; but from him that hath, ſhall be taken away that hee hath. Iob</hi> renders the reaſon: Becauſe <hi>Men haue forſaken the feare of the Lord.</hi> How many <hi>haue the faith in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons?</hi> forſake iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> if tumbling on the dunghill? and be aſhamed of <hi>Pauls chaine?</hi> Is this <hi>to ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called thee?</hi> to imitate the example of thy Sauiour? and to be a fellow-feeler of thy brothers affliction? If this goe before, what will follow? ſhall not the Lord <hi>mete to vs, as we haue meaſured to others?</hi> leaue vs, when we haue moſt need of comfort, ſeeing we cry, <hi>Stand afarre, come not neare me,</hi> to our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and friends in the time of affliction.</p>
            <p>Was it not <hi>Ionathans</hi> praiſe, that he was <hi>louely in life and death,</hi> and would not leaue his brother <hi>Dauid</hi> in all his troubles? and ſhall it not be thy duty and comfort to doe the like to all thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? The <hi>Butler</hi> is branded, that <hi>he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred not Ioſeph</hi> in his bands; and hence (probably) came that Prouerbe: <hi>No man remembreth the afflictions of Ioſeph.</hi> Yet we haue ſome more vnnaturall, who forſake men in their proſperity, and dayes of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14514:19"/> Gods promotion: they enuie <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe hee is <hi>annointed King from the ſheepe-fold:</hi> Cry, <hi>away with Amos, he muſt not prophecy at Bethel, for he was a figge-gatherer:</hi> and if <hi>Chriſt</hi> come out of <hi>Nazaret,</hi> be reputed the <hi>Carpenters ſonne;</hi> and aduanced by his heauenly Father; ſome will reiect him; others doubt of him; and too few receiue him.</p>
            <p>And (without miſ-apprehenſion be it ſpoken) I haue ſeene theſe two euils in the learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious of our times; Friends forſaken in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, enuied in proſperity: wee will not viſit the poore, if wee bee rich; neither regard them the Lord extraordinarily aduanceth. But theſe things ſhould not be ſo: why then ſay with <hi>Ruth, Nought but death ſhall part thee, and thy friend:</hi> follow him with thine affection whitherſoeuer he goeth; and if he <hi>fall amongst theeues,</hi> goe not <hi>by him,</hi> but <hi>looke on him;</hi> and to thy ability and his neceſſity relieue him: For this is thy Fathers proceeding; the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; the only way to be of others reſpected, when thou thy ſelfe art moſt afflicted.</p>
            <p>If pouerty would haue parted friends; naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made a ſeparation, meanneſſe of birth, or baſeneſſe of condition; then the Lord had neuer tooke pitie on thee; or, in affection been vnited to thee. Wherefore ſet the Lords patterne before thine eyes; and whatſoeuer hee beareth with, in his, doe thou the like alſo: and let not that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy loue from any of thy brethren, againſt which the <hi>God of loue</hi> neuer obiected, diſliked; or, for the which his affection was neuer ſeparated, weakened. I know this is thy dutie; but a thing,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14514:19"/> not eaſie to bee done; for, it is no weake, but a maine pitch of ſanctification, not to draw argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the meanneſſe of a mans birth, friends, education, former pouerty, or preſent neceſſity to withdraw, extenuate and ſeparate affection: but to loue, where, and in the ſame manner the Lord loueth: he that doth this, <hi>fleſh and blood neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed it to him.</hi> Then ſtriue for it; it is worth the obtaining; that it may be ſaid of thee, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of one, who performed this dutie: <hi>The Lord ſhew mercie to the houſe of</hi> Oneſiphorus; <hi>The Lord graunt he may finde mercie with the Lord at that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> And from this point of Gods affection to his children in affliction; we may all be encouraged to ſerue ſuch a maſter. Art thou his ſeruant, and ſonne? then doe not, with the <hi>Prodigall,</hi> run from him; or with <hi>Demas, embrace the world:</hi> for all creatures of that kind will faile and forſake thee in thy affliction; or if not, they will proue, but like <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, or the Phariſies, <hi>Miſerable Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Or, haſt thou not yet giuen vp thy name, and <hi>with a purpoſe of heart cleaued to the Lord?</hi> why then change thy maſter, and make choyce of him wee haue in hand.</p>
            <p>Who would not ſerue ſuch a man as will bee alwaies preſent with his people; haue an eye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them; call them by name, and relieue them according to their neceſſities? Shall not we then make election of the Lord? For his eye ſhall <hi>watch for thy good; his right hand ſhall be ouer thy face, and his left hand vnder thy head;</hi> and, <hi>thou ſhalt want no manner of thing.</hi> Art thou in bonds? hee ſhall viſit
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14514:20"/> thee. In danger? his Angels ſhall defend thee. In want? the creatures refreſh thee. Tempted by Satan? he ſhall fight for thee. Or in the pangs and ſhadow of death? yet he will bee with thee, that thou maiſt ſleepe ſoundly and ſecurely.</p>
            <p>Beloued, this I know, that if God be with vs, it is no matter who be againſt vs: but if hee bee not on our ſide, what will it profit vs to bee reſpected of the world? And ſay not in thy heart, <hi>Luſh, my mountaine is ſtrong, and I ſhall not be moued;</hi> for wee are but in the wilderneſſe, wee ſhall meet with fiery ſerpents, the ſtings of a guiltie and wounded ſpirit. <hi>Iordan,</hi> that type of death hath not looked vs in the face; at the moſt, wee haue not paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it: and doth not the day draw neere? is it not at hand? and if the Lord doe not then helpe thee, and be with thee, what ſhall become of thee? <hi>wofull</hi> will be that <hi>Hauen,</hi> where thou ſhalt be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>O that we did but know the worth of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in affliction! or how ioyfull a thing it is for his children to be aſſured of his affection! Well; the day of death and of iudgement ſhall declare it: and till then, the true worth will not bee fully knowne of the faithfull; or the want feelingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by the vngodly. Let me then entreat thee to ſtriue for his fauour; thinke no paines too great to obtaine it; neither be at peace till thou poſſeſſe it; for then thou maieſt haue comfort in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; ioy, amidſt ſorrow; and life, in death. No tidings ſo terrible, that ſhall make thee tremble; no former ſinne cauſe thee to feare; nor Satans
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14514:20"/> deadlieſt darts touch or pierce thee, if the Lord be with thee. Now then is the time to agree with him; take the opportunity, fore-ſlow it not; and build thou on this rocke once, and ſtand for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>A third point from the words may now be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, <hi>viZ.</hi> that,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>The fauour of God in affliction, onely giueth the faithfull ſatisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee that this good man did comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from no other ground, but from this, that <hi>The Lord thought on him.</hi> Neither is there any thing that could worke this effect, he being in ſo great affliction, except the Lords loue and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Many cry, who will ſhew vs any good?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4 6.</note> 
               <hi>But Lord lift thou the light of thy countenance vpon me.</hi> And <hi>whom haue I in heauen but thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 73.25.</note> 
               <hi>or in earth that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in compariſon of thee?</hi> No perſon, no thing. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is good</hi> (yea beſt) <hi>to draw neere to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd</hi> 28. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> for content in theſe dangers. <hi>Saul</hi> was a King, and yet when <hi>God</hi> was gone, could his kingdome yeeld him any comfort? <hi>BalſhaZZar</hi> in his bowles will quake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.6.</note> and his heart roll within him, <hi>if the Lords hand in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be ſtretched out againſt him.</hi> Why doth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell tremble and feare? Oh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>hee hath no confidence in the great Creator. Cain</hi> will <hi>curſe</hi> and <hi>cry</hi> to,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5.</note> when he cannot expect and reſt in a cheerfull acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Lord: but let all the creatures in the earth, and the whole hoaſt of <hi>Heauen</hi> band them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt vs, <hi>If God be with vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.</note> 
               <hi>who can be againſt vs</hi> to hurt vs, trouble vs? And what may bee the reaſon of this?</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14514:21"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Why, the Lord is the onely obiect of their loue, and he in whom their ſoule principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth: wherefore enioying him, they haue all they would.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.28.</note> Let <hi>Iacob</hi> heare that <hi>Ioſeph his ſonne is yet aliue, he hath enough.</hi> If the King <hi>come home ſafe, Ziba</hi> may keepe the land,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30.</note> for <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> is ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Could but the ſonne of <hi>Hamor</hi> match with <hi>Dinah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.19.</note> his Circumciſion will bee endured; and though the daughters in the countrey bee denied him, yet ſhall he be well contented. <hi>Giue</hi> but <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Luk</hi> 1.29.</note> and ſhe will not <hi>die.</hi> And let <hi>Simeon ſee his Sauiour</hi> and he will die. And how are theſe contrary effects produced? Why loue is the cauſe thereof: ſo let Gods children enioy the ſubiect of their affection, they will reſt in it with full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation in all affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Becauſe they beleeue then, and know that <hi>all ſhall worke together for good</hi> at their latter end.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> For being aſſured of the one, they neuer need to doubt of the other: and grant but the firſt, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond will enſue of neceſſity. Will it not reioyce the poore patient, that his Phyſition doth affect him? for then he is aſſured, that if he can, hee will (and God can) cure him. If we haue the Iudge for our friend and father, what need wee to feare the many inditements preferred againſt vs? Let <hi>Moſes</hi> haue the Lord to looke vpon him, <hi>Pharaohs</hi> frownes cannot feare him: and let God but thinke on vs, and we thinke on him (he by affection, wee by faith), we need not to ſhake or ſhadder: but walke on cheerfully and reſolutely <hi>in the valleyes of teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>and the very ſhadow of death. Dauid</hi> in his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14514:21"/> greateſt troubles ſpeaketh thus to the Lord; <hi>Thou haſt giuen ioy in my heart, more then of the time, when their corne and their new wine were multiplied.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>In peace together will I lye downe and ſleepe; for thou Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah alone wilt ſeate me in confidence; preſerue my ſoule in ſafetie.</hi> Now from this point thus proued, we learne theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> And firſt, whats the true cauſe, why ſo many are ſhaken with euery blaſt, and flie like chaffe before the leaſt wind of affliction? Alas! they haue not made the Lord their portion, neither bee aſſured of his affection: their loue leanes on ſome other ſubiect; and that once failing, they fall for euer. He that affecteth the earth, if it grow barren, hee will ſtill be bawling: and he that expects treaſures from a farre; let the wind but riſe, and the water ſwell, his body will ſweat, and his ſoule be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled within him: the ſea is not ſo much toſſed, but he is as much terrified: the one caſts not vp more mire and mud, then the other feare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.5. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23.</note> Shall wee thinke that <hi>Iudas</hi> would haue hanged himſelfe; <hi>Saul</hi> fallen on his owne ſpeare; or ſo wiſe a wight as <hi>Achitophel,</hi> proued his owne executioner; if God had been the obiect of their affection, and they put confidence in him in their affliction? No: it had been a thing impoſſible. And therefore we may hence ſafely conclude, that the want of the aſſurance of Gods ſauour is the true cauſe, why men in diſcontent and croſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their owne executioners. For that which they affect moſt, wanting power to content and preſerue them, or being remoued from them; they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14514:22"/> hauing no other God in their preſent apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, often become their owne bloudy Butchers, to drowne, hang, or murther themſelues. And doe but obſerue it, and what I haue ſpoken, you ſhall find verified by experience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And in the ſecond place we may hence learne the true ground, why Gods children haue ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced in affliction; and it is this and no other, namely their aſſurance of Gods fauour and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. He that beleeueth in the Lord by faith, is linked to him in loue, and perſwaded that God thinkes on him, will embrace death, deſire iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and neuer tremble at the moſt terrible ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> will goe <hi>hee knowes not whither; Daniel</hi> into the Denne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> 6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.6.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> to priſon, hauing this confidence of the Lords fauour. <hi>Iacob</hi> will leaue his fathers houſe, <hi>Ruth</hi> runne into a ſtrange Countrie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.23.</note> and <hi>Christ</hi> embrace <hi>the Croſſe, endure the ſhame,</hi> when God thinkes on them. How ſhould <hi>Iob</hi> haue endured the ſtealth of his cattel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job,</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> burning of his corne, and the ſudden death of all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when their bones were bruiſed and broken; their bloud and braines ſprinkled and ſpread on the poſts and timber; his VViues bitter words, <hi>Curſe God and dye</hi> (for ſo the place is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; for it's probable Satan ſpared her life to that purpoſe to tempt him; and it was the end he aimed at, <hi>He will curſe thee to thy face:</hi> why ſhould wee then imagine, that hee put not that tart and cruell phraſe into her mouth? for he is wiſe in his proceedings) if the certaintie of the Lords loue had not ſupported him? Had it once been poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14514:22"/> for fraile men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> and weake women to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured burning, hewing aſunder, and to be rent on the <hi>Racke,</hi> but vpon this ground? VVhy then, ſee the true cauſe of ioy in ſorrow, and giue the Lord his deſerued praiſe, <hi>whoſe power is the moſt made manifeſt in our weakeneſſe, wofulneſſe, wretchedneſſe,</hi> 2. Cor. 12.9.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Finally, wouldeſt thou be able to ſtand in the euill day, and the ſad times of tentation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution? then ſtriue more and more, to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lords affection: endeauour to poſſeſſe <hi>Dauids</hi> darling; get Gods affection once ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in thy heart; be ſure of this, and thou ſhalt endure the greateſt ſtorme; cut the ſtrongeſt ſtreames of the raging tide, and land ſafe at the hauen of Heauen. VVe, in pollicy, prepare cloakes for wet, prouiſion for winter, and a ſtaffe againſt the time of decrepit old age; and ſhall wee not prouide for death and iudgement? VVhat can ſupport thee in the times of trouble, &amp; the hower of thy departure, but ſome perſwaſion of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor? Could <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Horſes, the Rich Mans pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Fooles great barnes, or <hi>Ieſabel</hi> her pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if thou hadſt them? No, no: theſe are but a vaine thing, a ſandy foundation, and a ſtaffe of Reed, that will either ſtocke thee faſt, or breake in ſhiuers, piercing thy hands through with many ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the feare of God thinke on this one thing: for death will come, and will not tarry; and if thou haue not this fixed faſt in the furrowes of thy heart, little pleaſure canſt thou haue in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14514:23"/> death at death. And becauſe we dreame (but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues, and that too too often), in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are in the Lords fauour highly, principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in proſperitie; be thou the more carefull to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this thing. Wee haue a common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb, that A good thing cannot be made too ſure: and what better then this in all the world? And for the better triall of thy ſelfe in the matter, take theſe rules in the meane while, till thou haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned better.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, if the Lord loue thee, then thou doeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect thy affection againe vpon him. He <hi>ſheds his</hi> loue firſt <hi>abroad in thy heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.</note> and then thou art en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the loue of him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> 73 27.</note> For as I firſt giue heate to my bed, and then it giues me warmth the night after: ſo the Lords loue heateth my heart, and then I thence forward affect him: certainely he that loues the Lord, is loued of him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, if the Lord loue thee, then he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale himſelfe vnto thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially in prayer, and that familiarly. When thou haſt called on his Name, hath hee giuen thee a gracious and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable anſwere? Haſt thou felt a ſecret voice of the ſpirit, ſpeaking to the eare of thy ſoule, <hi>Thy prayer is heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>and thy requeſt come before the Lord?</hi> (for God, like man, giueth the greateſt gifts, and manifeſteth himſelf to his children the moſt in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret). <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then be thou of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, for the Lord thinkes on thee. Beſides, canſt thou ſpeake by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 21.45.</note> that hee hath kept couenant with thee, and performed his promiſe <hi>(for his promiſes are Yea and Amen to all he loueth)?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> then maiſt thou haue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14514:23"/> hope.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 27 3.</note> VVhat peace haſt thou found wrought in thy ſoule?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.9.</note> How hath he watered thee euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? humbled thee in proſperitie, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee in aduerſitie? Haſt thou an experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall knowledge of his proceedings? feare not then, he will doe thee good, and no euill;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note> and he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer weary (for that were to croſſe his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) in weldoing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And doeſt thou reiect the <hi>Arme of fleſh and bloud;</hi> denie thy owne power, and onely rely vpon the Lord? I then dare giue thee my word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.11.12.</note> that he ſhall neuer faile thee, or in the greateſt danger for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee.</p>
            <p>Be thou aſſured once, that theſe things are in thee; and the like done for thee; and thou ſhalt be as ſecure and ſafe from all dangers in life and death, as the leaſt drop of water in the bottome of the deepe Ocean ſea is from the exhalation of the Summers Sun; or that graine of ſand, which poſſeſſeth the very center of the Globe, is from motion, or the footes trampling, ſcattering.</p>
            <p>One thing more may yet bee obſerued out of the words, <hi>thinketh on me,</hi> which is, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>The Lord will deliuer the faithfull from all dangers; free them in a conuenient ſeaſon from all afflictions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 91. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For this is the true expoſition of the phraſe, as the words following doe declare euidently, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Noah</hi> ſhall not be drowned in the old world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> but be freed from all dangers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Let</hi> ſhall come ſafe to little <hi>Zoar. Moſes</hi> flee to, and returne in health,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.</note> from the land of <hi>Madian. Ioſeph</hi> may be ſold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.</note> yet God can preſerue him ſafe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.</note> and <hi>Eſau</hi> expect the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14514:24"/> time of mourning to be reuenged on his brother <hi>Iacob,</hi> yet ſhall he come againe, and find fauour in his eyes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Let <hi>Dauid</hi> be hunted like a Partridge, the rauening Kite ſhall neuer catch him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 45.5.</note> and <hi>Baruch</hi> ſhall haue his life, though many periſh for a prey. <hi>Peter</hi> may be in priſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.19.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12 7.8.</note> yet ſhall the gates be caſt off their hinges, his bolts be looſed, and hee ſet at libertie.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim</hi> 4.17.18.</note> And though <hi>Paul</hi> be forſaken of all men, yet <hi>God ſhall aſsist him, free him out of the mouth of the Lyon, and preſerue him to his heauenly kingdome.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 1.21.</note> this is moſt certain, that either in life he ſhal let them looſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 22 20.</note> to runne at libertie; or by death free them from the euill to come. And reaſon may be rendred why it ſhall be ſo:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For the Lord hath ſo promiſed and purpoſed, and ſhall not <hi>his counſell ſtand?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.21.</note> and his word abide for euer? Did he euer faile in keeping couenant? or haue his promiſes at any time been preuented? No,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5.18.</note> no: <hi>Let Heauen and Earth paſſe away, one iot of his word ſhall not moue, but be verified, certainely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.</note> For ſhall God proue a lyer? breake promiſe? Away with this; he cannot, he will not. God is not like man, promiſing what he neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to performe:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> for <hi>all the promiſes made by him, are Yea and Amen in Christ Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> And this will hee doe of loue to his children, and hatred to the wicked. God will not haue the vncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to reioyce in the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of little <hi>Dauid</hi> his Annointed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.26.27.</note> or the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Canaanites to tread vnder-foot the ſanctified ſeede of old <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.10.11. <hi>&amp;c. Exod.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> may lay great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens on the <hi>Iewes,</hi> yet the more he doth vex them,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14514:24"/> they ſhall multiply, grow and vex him. This hath been a reaſon of force in former time, and may continue ſtill to confirme this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> And from this point the faithfull muſt learne patience, and not to make haſte,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> or mourne <hi>as men without hope,</hi> for it's but <hi>a very little while, and then He that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarrie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37.</note> 
               <hi>The Husbandman muſt patiently expect the time of harueſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5 7.</note> the Mariner waite with content for wind and tide; and the VVatchman for the dawning of the day: wee muſt alſo tarrie the Lords leiſure; bee ſtrong, and he, in the fitteſt ſeaſon, will comfort our ſoules. <hi>Dauid</hi> being aſſured, that he ſhould ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in <hi>the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,</hi> did not faint,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.13.</note> but expect with patience the time appointed; and his patterne muſt be our practiſe; ſeeing it was grounded and ſprang from the point we haue in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Againe, as by this point we are taught for the preſent, to be patient; ſo to confirme our faith, for time future. And what can more ſtrengthen it, then certaintie of full freedome, and a totall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie from all the euill that ſhall befall them, 2. Cor. 4.16.17?</p>
            <p>But we thinke not ſeriouſly of this thing, and that's the cauſe, we hang downe the loynes of our mindes; <hi>and that which is halting is readie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>vpon the least</hi> rub, <hi>to be turned out of the way.</hi> Wherefore let vs conſider how he hath in former time deliuered his; and it will be a notable prop to ſupport our ſtaggering minds; and a ſure baſe, and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for faith to reſt it ſelfe vpon. Now the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14514:25"/> kinds and meanes be many.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God can ſtop the mouthes of the raging Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they ſhall not rent the very garment of his children, as we ſee in Dan. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, he is able to preſerue vs in the fier from burning, as the <hi>Buſh</hi> was, Exod. 3.2. and the three children in the furnace, Dan. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in bringing iudgements on our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, and breaking the teeth of the Lion, as of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Exod. 14; of <hi>Haman,</hi> Eſter 7; and <hi>Herod,</hi> Acts 12.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Beſides, if not ſo, he can change the heart, and cauſe <hi>Paul</hi> a bloudy perſecutor, to become a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Chriſtian ſouldier,</hi> Acts 9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Furthermore, he wanteth not skill or power to deliuer <hi>Paul,</hi> by ſetting the enemies at ods one with another, as hee did the Sadduces and the Phariſees, Acts 21.31. &amp; 23.10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, when their enemies are vpon their backes, tidings may come to <hi>Saul,</hi> that the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines are about to inuade the land: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> may eſcape the danger, 1. Sam. 23.27. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Moreouer, he can giue his ſeruants power and boldneſſe to dare their foes to their face, as he did <hi>Paul</hi> and others, in ſo much as they ſhall be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated, and ſent away, Acts 4.8. &amp;c. Acts 16.37, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> And what ſhall I more ſay? God can compell <hi>Balaam</hi> to bleſſe; <hi>Caiphas</hi> to prophecie; and the Whale to preſerue <hi>Ionah,</hi> when the ſhip would not ſaue him. And is his power yet weakened, his wiſedome decreaſed, or his will altered, changed?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14514:25"/> No, in no wiſe: for there is no <hi>ſhadow of turning with the Lord;</hi> therefore feare not, faile not, faint not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> But it will bee obiected, that <hi>Abel</hi> was ſlaine; <hi>Iames</hi> beheaded, and many of Chriſts members murdered.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that if we keep,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> and liue in ſome cloſe ſinne, the Lord will not deliuer vs; for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſome iniquitie, may procure danger, yea death too.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But Chriſt neuer ſinned, yet was not deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> True: yet vntill the appointed time hee was, and ſo ſhall all his members: but when that hower comes, then they muſt goe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> Againe, though God do not deliuer euerie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in particular, yet he will the Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as we may ſee in the foure great Monarchies of the world; how one were d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, onely a remnant that were Gods people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and ſhall till the end of the world. For was not the Church as ſafe in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as in the land and limits of Canaan?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>3</label> Againe, God doth deliuer his from deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in affliction: ſo that trouble ſhall not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden them, but rather reioyce them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>4</label> Againe, his promiſes are alwaies limited, ſo farre forth as they may make for his glory and our good: and what can we haue more?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>5</label> Againe, theſe promiſes muſt bee vnderſtood compleatly, either in this life, or in the world to come, when all the faithfull ſhall be deliuered for euer.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14514:26"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>6</label> In concluſion; if wee bee comforted in death more then life; are we not deliuered? And if we were not, what doe we looſe, but earth, and gaine heauen? For daily danger, or violent death ſhall not depriue the righteous of a better life.</p>
            <p>This then being thus; be of good comfort for the preſent; feare not any future dangers; but plucke vp your hearts, and gird vp the loynes of your mindes: Goe on through good report, and euill report; be reſolute ſouldiers of <hi>Ieſus Christ;</hi> march on valiantly, and feare not their feare. For mauger their malice, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall ſerue his dayes; <hi>Paul</hi> finiſh his worke, and <hi>Iohns</hi> life be prolonged, vntill his taske be ended. Let <hi>Balaam,</hi> the Pope, curſe; <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the Turke purſue; <hi>Gallio,</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, iudge; <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> the Prieſt, condemne; nay, let Satan rage, his inſtruments band them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together, and all the crawling Locuſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend out of the nethermoſt hell; yet I haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and euer will, that the Lords Annointed ſhal raigne, his people encreaſe more and more, the word daily runne, Babylon be razed downe to the ground, the houſe of <hi>Bethel</hi> builded and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, till the Sonne of God returne againe in his greateſt glorie. When all wicked and vngodly men ſhall taſt of the ſecond death; be bound hand and foot, and ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fier: And euerie vpright and honeſt heart ſhall haue al teares wiped from his eyes, fetters from his feete, manacles from his fingers; runne to and fro in the new Ieruſalem that is aboue; and with <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſhowt for ioy, as <hi>Dauid</hi> and the people did, when the Ark
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14514:26"/> came home ſafe into the Citie: and then ſhall it bee knowne, whether God had, or not, power to tread downe Satan, and his ſhauelings vnder foote; and preſerue his people vnto his heauenlie Kingdome. To which God, for this hope, be prayſe throughout all generations, for euer and euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
